<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-07-13T23:54:23+10:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Nalini Joshi, mathematician</title><entry><title type="html">Transcendentality</title><link href="/2021/07/13/transcendentality.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transcendentality" /><published>2021-07-13T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2021-07-13T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>/2021/07/13/transcendentality</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2021/07/13/transcendentality.html">&lt;p&gt;The topic of these posts lies at the intersection of many directions in mathematics. From time to time, you will see aspects of dynamical systems theory, asymptotics, mathematical physics, 
differential or difference Galois theory, reflection group theory and algebraic geometry. I hope my posts will be accessible for all readers. (Feel free to email me to ask for additional explanations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journey starts with the mathematical term “transcendental”. Suppose we have the counting numbers
\(1, 2, 3, \ldots\).
Addition and subtraction of counting numbers, like&lt;br /&gt;
\(1+3=4, 5-8=-3, \ldots\),
lead to the integers \(\mathbb{Z}\).
Multiplication and division of (non-zero) integers lead to rational numbers \(\mathbb{Q}\), like
\(1/2, 0.3333\ldots\).
There are many more numbers beyond these number systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose you want zeroes of polynomials, like \(x^2-2=0\). A solution of a polynomial equation with integer coefficients is an algebraic number, like \(\sqrt{2}\). 
But this is not the end of the construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are numbers called “transcendental numbers” that escape any algebraic construction. It is impossible to write them as a finite or repeating decimal expansion. 
Because it is difficult to write them down completely, they appear to be mysterious. They lie in regions on the number line like those in old maps filled with 
drawings of fabulous monsters. But, we know from the widespread appearance of the number π in every part of mathematics, that they arise everywhere in real life. 
This post is about functions that play a similar role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get to such functions, imagine replacing counting numbers with polynomials.  Multiplication and division of polynomials lead to rational functions. 
Solving polynomials of more than one variable leads to algebraic functions. Functions that are not algebraic are called &lt;i&gt;transcendental functions&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sequence of steps, a “ladder of transcendentality”,
that leads to more and more complicated constructions of transcendental functions. At the base level are familiar transcendental functions, like exponential, 
trigonometric and logarithmic functions. But there are higher level functions that escape any algebraic operations applied to these earlier-known functions or their compositions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exploration of transcendental functions reaches back at least as far as Euler in 1755. The enduring question of whether a newly 
 discovered function can be expressed in terms of earlier known transcendental functions is difficult to answer automatically. Like for transcendental numbers, 
 the first question here is to ask whether there exist algebraic relations between them. Derivatives or differences of transcendental functions also play a 
 crucial role in answering such questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each new level of exploration aims to capture functions that escape the previous steps. There is a hierarchy of known cases given as 
 solutions of differential or difference equations. Functions in the hierarchy are categorized according to whether or not they result from operations called 
 &lt;i&gt;classical operations&lt;/i&gt; applied to functions at a previous step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what are the currently known transcendental functions that are furthest away from polynomials, at the top of the known hierarchy of functions solving polynomial differential 
 or difference equations? They are solutions of equations
 called the &lt;i&gt;discrete Painlevé equations&lt;/i&gt; or &lt;i&gt;Painlevé equations&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;powered by &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The topic of these posts lies at the intersection of many directions in mathematics. From time to time, you will see aspects of dynamical systems theory, asymptotics, mathematical physics, differential or difference Galois theory, reflection group theory and algebraic geometry. I hope my posts will be accessible for all readers. (Feel free to email me to ask for additional explanations.)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is this thing called Painlevé?</title><link href="/2021/07/13/what-is-this-thing-called-painleve.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is this thing called Painlevé?" /><published>2021-07-13T00:00:00+10:00</published><updated>2021-07-13T00:00:00+10:00</updated><id>/2021/07/13/what-is-this-thing-called-painleve</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2021/07/13/what-is-this-thing-called-painleve.html">&lt;p&gt;Imagine you want to define “new” functions, where &lt;i&gt;new&lt;/i&gt; means functions that cannot be expressed in terms of functions you already know. Imagine that equations they satisfy arise in a wide range of applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the starting point of the journey that led to nonlinear differential equations called the &lt;i&gt;Painlevé equations&lt;/i&gt; and difference equations called the &lt;i&gt;disrcrete Painlevé equations&lt;/i&gt;. The aim of this post is to describe this mathematical journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This journey and its associated discoveries are so broad and the details are so rich that I will have to explain its steps in different staging posts. For now, the impatient reader may want to jump in with both feet by watching the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.math.ucla.edu/dls/nalini-joshi&quot;&gt;videos of lectures&lt;/a&gt; I gave at UCLA or reading the introductory article I wrote for Notices of the &lt;a href=&quot;ams.org&quot;&gt;AMS&lt;/a&gt;, whose &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ams.org/journals/notices/202006/rnoti-p797.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;  is available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those patient enough to go on the journey with me. I invite you to the next post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;powered by &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Imagine you want to define “new” functions, where new means functions that cannot be expressed in terms of functions you already know. Imagine that equations they satisfy arise in a wide range of applications.</summary></entry></feed>